Next up, we have sets sets are also mutable data types, and they allow you to only store
immutable items in them in an unsorted way.
Sets are mutable meaning that you can add items to them, you can remove items from them,
they can contain other immutable types like integer string, tuple because tuple is immutable,
but not lists, not sets and not dictionaries, which are themselves mutable.
Unlike a list or tuple, sets can only contain unique items in them.
If you make a set and you try to add items from the set, instead of a list where you can
have as many copies as you want, the set is just going to toss that away.
And the benefit of this is that sets are fast, they have fast membership testing.
We'll talk about this a little bit later, but because the items in them are immutable,
you can run a function called a hash function, and very quickly figure out, is the item
I'm looking for in the set or not, without having to look at every single value in it.
And you can also use powerful set operations, like union, intersection, difference.
I'm not going to jump into these during the course of this chapter, but there are some
exercises around them, quick set, cheat, cheat here at the top, and let's talk about sets.
So if lists have square brackets and tuples are parentheses and commas, you might think
that sets are curly braces, but there's an aha here.
We try to create an empty set with just curly braces.
We are instead going to end up with a dictionary, because dictionaries are also surrounded by curly
braces, so if you need to create an empty set in this case, you will want to use the set constructor
and that will give you the empty set that you are looking for.
Set can have one item in them, or multiples.
If we have a set where I tried to pass in three, three and four, can anyone on zoom tell me
how many items will be in the set?
Two, awesome.
Because sets can't contain duplicate values. If you have a list of names,
and you want it to very quickly duplicate this list, you can actually just pass it into the
second structure, no more duplicates. So one of the very handy use cases for sets cannot contain
mutable types. Without having to always look at the cheat sheet, how do we know what types are
mutable, what types are not, shortcut to check for mutability, is to use the built-in hash function.
Can I call hash on an integer? Yes. Can I call hash on a string? Yes.
Can I call hash on a list? No, it's mutable. It's an unhashable type.
What happens if I try to have a set with a list in it?
I'm going to get that same error unhashable type list. You're probably going to see this
exception quite a bit, so I encourage you to remember it. When you run into exceptions like this,
just read them from the bottom up and think where else have I seen this exception, and that's going
to help you get to the root of the problem. Now sets don't have an order. So if I put a bunch of items
into a set, there is no guarantee at all that they will be in the same order that I put them into.
Because in sets order does not matter. What is going to happen if I try to get the zero with item
in the set? Can I do this? Nope. It's going to blow up and say a set object is not
subscriptable. That makes a whole lot of sense, right? Sets don't have an order. There is no item
at the zero with index. In the same vein, I cannot say my set zero equals some other item,
because again there is no order in sets and sets do not support item assignment. If you do want to add
and remove from sets, you can use the add operation, and again because I'm calling this on my set,
and my set is mutable. That does in fact change it. I can also call the discard operation
and that goes ahead and removes the item from the set. If I had two sets and I wanted to combine
them together, I could use the update method. So I could say that colors are red and orange.
Oops, I'm going to name this colors and numbers are a set that is 1, 2, and 3.
So if I look at my colors, I could call colors. update and pass in my numbers.
And now I have a new set. Remember set is mutable. I called dot update on it and that has
in fact changed the data in it. There are set operations like difference intersection.
I'm not going to cover them, but there is a section on those in the set operations cheat sheet
on the course website. So set operations are the most useful and most powerful feature of sets.
You can quickly figure out what items are the same between two sets. What items are different
and do that in a very, very performant way. Next up, we have dictionaries.
These are the dictionaries are a data type that allows to store key and value pairs.
Dictionaries themselves aren't mutable, but just like sets, dictionary keys can only be
immutable. Why? Because dictionary keys need to be hashable. Dictionaries allow fast item look up
and fast membership testing. You can quickly say, given a key is this key in my dictionary or not.
And that's because the hash of the key is compared with the hash of the keys in the dictionary.
Don't have to look through each item in that dictionary and say, are you the item? Are you the
item that I'm looking for? So can I have a list as a dictionary in a key?
Or I'm sorry, a list as a key in the dictionary. I ask that question correctly. I would get a better answer.
No, right? So a list is mutable. Dictionary keys can only be immutable. We cannot have
mutable data types as dictionary keys. Can we have a tuple as a dictionary key?
Yes, tuples are immutable. So we can use them as a dictionary key. I have a dictionary
cheat sheet here for you.